Last update: August 2, 2022

Contact Details Stanford University Telephone: +1 (650) 656-0855 Department of Statistics E-mail: ignat@stanford.edu

> 390 Jane Stanford Way, Website: https://nignatiadis.github.io/ Stanford, CA 94305, USA Google Scholar: user=KH3jpkoAAAAJ

RESEARCH Interests I am interested in the development of interpretable statistical methods, accompanied by robust software implementations, for the analysis of datasets generated from modern, high-throughput technologies. From a statistical perspective, this interest encompasses Empirical Bayes analysis, causal inference, multiple testing and statistics in the presence of contextual side-information.

EDUCATION

Stanford University

Stanford, California, USA

• Ph.D. in Statistics. (GPA 4.24)

Thesis advisor: Stefan Wager

Thesis title: Nonparametric perspectives on empirical Bayes.

Heidelberg University

Heidelberg, Germany

2015 - 2016

2011 - 2015

09/2016 - 06/2022

• M.Sc. Scientific Computing, Grade 1.0 Thesis advisors: Wolfgang Huber and Enno Mammen

• B.Sc. Mathematics, Grade 1.0 with distinction Thesis advisors: Wolfgang Huber and Rainer Dahlhaus

• B.Sc. Molecular Biotechnology, Grade 1.0 2010 - 2013

AWARDS AND Fellowships

Jerome H. Friedman Applied Statistics Dissertation Award

2022

For developing methodology that uses side information for increased power in multiple testing problems and for developing approaches to inference in empirical Bayes problems.

Ric Weiland Graduate Fellowship in the Humanities & Sciences

2020 - 2021

This fellowship is awarded to exceptional rising fourth year doctoral candidates in the humanities, social sciences, mathematics, and statistics upon departmental or programmatic nomination.

Departmental Teaching Assistant Award, Statistics Department, Stanford

2018 2013

iGEM Grand Prize Winner & Best Foundational Advance

The International Genetically Engineered Machine competition with Team Heidelberg at MIT.

Deutschlandstipendium, Heidelberg University, Germany

2011 - 2013

This scholarship is awarded to talented and high-achieving students at public and state recognised institutions of higher education in Germany and is supported by the German Federal Government.

Bronze medal at the International Biology Olympiad, Changwon, South Korea

Journal Publications

- 1. Ignatiadis, N. and Wager, S. (2021). Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis. Journal of the American Statistical Association, Theory & Methods (forthcoming). Selected as a discussion paper by the editors of JASA. The discussion will take place at JSM 2022.
- 2. Ignatiadis, N., Saha, S., Sun D. L. and Muralidharan, O. (2021). Empirical Bayes mean estimation with nonparametric errors via order statistic regression on replicated data. Journal of the American Statistical Association, Theory & Methods (forthcoming).
- 3. Ignatiadis, N. and Huber, W. (2021). Covariate powered cross-weighted multiple testing. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B. 83, 720-751.
- 4. Karacosta, L. G., Anchang, B., Ignatiadis, N., Kimmey, S.C., Benson, J.A., Shrager, J.B., Tibshirani, R., Bendall, S.C. and Plevritis, S.K. (2019). Mapping lung cancer epithelial-mesenchymal transition states and trajectories with single-cell resolution. Nature Communications, 1010, 5887.
- 5. Ignatiadis, N., Klaus, B., Zaugg, J. B. and Huber, W. (2016). Data-driven hypothesis weighting increases detection power in genome-scale multiple testing. Nature Methods, 13(7), 577-580.
- 6. Beer, R., Herbst, K., Ignatiadis, N., Kats, I., et al. (2014). Creating functional engineered variants of the single-module non-ribosomal peptide synthetase IndC by T domain exchange. Molecular BioSystems, 10(7), 1709-1718.

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

7. Ignatiadis, N. and Wager, S. (2019). Covariate-Powered Empirical Bayes Estimation. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 32 (NeurIPS 2019).

Preprints

- 8. Eckles, D., Ignatiadis, N. (corresponding author), Wager, S. and Wu, H. (2022). **Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs.** Working paper.
- 9. Ignatiadis, N. and Lolas, P. (2021). σ -Ridge: group-regularized ridge regression via empirical Bayes noise level cross-validation. Working paper.

Invited discussions

International Seminar on Selective Inference (ISSI)

December 2020

Discussant of the talk 'Clipper: p-value-free FDR control on high-throughput data from two conditions' by Prof. Jingyi Jessica Li.

Software

R packages in Bioconductor:

- IHW: Independent Hypothesis Weighting for multiple testing with side-information.
- IHWpaper: Companion to the IHW package facilitating reproducibility.

Julia packages in the official registry:

- Aurora.jl: Empirical Bayes mean estimation with nonparametric errors on replicated data.
- Empirikos.jl: Nonparametric empirical Bayes confidence intervals.
- RegressionDiscontinuity.jl: Basic functionality for analyzing sharp regression discontinuity designs.
- SigmaRidgeRegression.jl: σ -Ridge for regression with features that can be partitioned into groups.
- SmoothingSplines.jl: Nonparametric regression using smoothing splines.
- Contributions to Distributions.jl, GLM.jl, Lasso.jl, MultipleTesting.jl and others.

Industry experience

Google AdsMetrics, Mountain View, USA

Summer 2019

Data science intern with Omkar Muralidharan, Sujayam Saha and Dennis L. Sun.

RESEARCH APPOINTMENTS

Biomedical Informatics, Stanford, California, USA

2021 - Present

Research assistant in the group of Prof. Nigam Shah funded by the NHLBI R01 grant 'Applying statistical learning tools to personalize cardiovascular treatment'.

Statistics Department, Stanford, California, USA

2017 - 2021

Research assistant with Prof. Stefan Wager working on empirical Bayes and causal inference problems.

European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany

2014 - 2016

Research assistant in the group of Dr. Wolfgang Huber.

Talks and Presentations

Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis.

December 2021

CMStatistics: Advances in empirical Bayes methodology

Virtual presentation

Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs.

November 2021

Fourth Annual Berkeley-Stanford Econometrics Jamboree

UC Berkeley, California, USA

Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs.

November 2021

Causal Science Conference

Stanford University, California, USA

Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs.

August 2021

Joint Statistical Meetings (JSM): Causal Inference When Resources Are Limited

Virtual presentation

σ -Ridge: group regularized ridge regression via empirical Bayes noise level cross-validation.

April 2021

Statistics seminar at Vrije Universiteit (VU) Amsterdam campus

Virtual presentation

Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis.

April 2021

International Seminar on Selective Inference (ISSI)

Virtual presentation

Bias-Aware Confidence Intervals for Empirical Bayes Analysis.

August 2020

Joint Statistical Meetings (JSM): Causality in Statistical Data Science

Virtual presentation

Covariate-Powered Empirical Bayes Estimation.

January 2020

Blue seminar at the European Molecular Biology Laboratory

European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL), Heidelberg, Germany

Covariate-Powered Empirical Bayes Estimation.

December 2019

11th International Conference on Multiple Comparison Procedures

National Taiwan University (NTU), Taipei, Taiwan

Bias-Aware Confidence Intervals for Empirical Bayes Estimation.

May 2019

Atlantic Causal Inference Conference (ACIC)

McGill University, Montreal, Canada

Covariate powered cross-weighted multiple testing.

February 2019

Statistics Industrial Affiliates Conference

Stanford University, California, USA

Covariate-powered cross-weighted multiple testing with FDR Control.

February 2018

Workshop: Post-selection Inference and Multiple Testing Institut de Mathématiques de Toulouse, Toulouse, France

MultipleTesting.jl: Simultaneous Statistical Inference in Julia.

June 2017

Lightning talk at JuliaCon UC Berkeley, California, USA

Data-driven hypothesis weighting increases detection power in

July 2016

genome-scale multiple testing.

Genome Biology Seminar at the European Molecular Biology Laboratory European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL), Heidelberg, Germany

Teaching

Instructor at Stanford

STATS 302: Applied Statistics Ph.D. Qualifying Exam Workshop.

Summer 2020

Teaching Assistant (TA) at Stanford

STATS 315B: Modern Applied Statistics: Data Mining.

STATS 361: Causal Inference.

STATS 305B: Applied Statistics II.

STATS 305B: Applied Statistics II.

STATS 315A: Modern Applied Statistics: Learning.

STATS 300A: Theory of Statistics I.

STATS 300A: Theory of Statistics I.

STATS 366 (BIOS 221): Modern Statistics for Modern Biology.

STATS 218: Introduction to Stochastic Processes II.

Spring 2021

Winter 2020

Summer 2017 & 2018, Fall 2019

STATS 218: Introduction to Stochastic Processes II.

STATS 290: Computing for Data Science.

Winter 2018 Fall 2017

STATS 305A: Introduction to Statistical Modeling. STATS 191: Introduction to Applied Statistics.

Winter 2017

STATS 141 (BIOS 141): Biostatistics.

Fall 2016

Trainer at EMBL (European Molecular Biology Laboratory)

Introductory Course: Statistical Bioinformatics using R and Bioconductor

October 2015

PEER REVIEW

Statistics journals

Annals of Statistics (AoS), Bernoulli, Biometrics, Biometrika, Electronic Journal of Statistics (EJS), Journal of the American Statistical Association (JASA), Journal of Business & Economic Statistics (JBES), Journal of Causal Inference (JCI), Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics (JCGS), Journal of Statistical Software (JSS), Statistical Papers, Statistical Science

Other journals

Bioinformatics, Bioinformatics Advances, Heliyon, Journal of Cell Science, Management Science, Operations Research, PeerJ

Conferences

AISTATS (2021), NeurIPS (2021, 2022), ICLR (2022)